June 1979, Iranian revolutionaries
ژوئن ۱۹۷۹، انقلابیون ایرانی
published their first draft constitution.
اولین پیش‌نویس قانون اساسی را منتشر کردند.
Strong parliament, elected president,
مجلس قوی، رئیس‌جمهور منتخب،
independent
قوه قضائیه
judiciary, checks and balances.
مستقل، تفکیک قوا.
Zero supreme leaders, no guardian
صفر رهبر، بدون شورای
council. Not a single word about
نگهبان. حتی یک کلمه درباره
religious vetoes for elections.
وتوی مذهبی در انتخابات نبود.
Then, December 1979, a completely
بعد، دسامبر ۱۹۷۹، یک قانون اساسی
different constitution gets approved.
کاملاً متفاوت تصویب شد.
11 major powers concentrated in one
۱۱ اختیار اصلی در دست یک
person, appointed for life.
نفر متمرکز شد، منصوب مادام‌العمر.
He can dismiss presidents,
او می‌تواند رئیس‌جمهور را برکنار کند،
overrule parliament and command the
مجلس را نقض کند و فرماندهی
military. Same revolution with two
ارتش را داشته باشد. همان انقلاب با دو
totally different documents.
سند کاملاً متفاوت.
One promised democracy, the other was
یکی وعده دموکراسی داد، دیگری
built to prevent it.
ساخته شد تا جلویش را بگیرد.
So what happened between June and
پس بین ژوئن و دسامبر
December and why are
چه اتفاقی افتاد و چرا
people still dying for it?
مردم هنوز برایش می‌میرند؟
You'll see two big explanations online.
دو توضیح بزرگ در اینترنت می‌بینید.
One side says "it's just an oppressive
یک طرف می‌گوید «فقط یک تئوکراسی
theocracy, Islam plus dictatorship.
سرکوبگر است، اسلام به‌علاوه دیکتاتوری.
Nothing changes until Iranians
هیچ چیز عوض نمی‌شود تا ایرانیان
get their own enlightenment."
روشنگری خودشان را داشته باشند.»
The other side says "it's all America's
طرف دیگر می‌گوید «همه‌اش تقصیر
fault, the 1953 coup broke Iran,
آمریکاست، کودتای ۱۹۵۳ ایران را شکست،
everything since then
همه چیز از آن موقع
is blowback." Both are wrong, and they're
واکنش است.» هر دو اشتباه‌اند، و اشتباه‌اند
wrong because neither
چون هیچ‌کدام توضیح نمی‌دهند
explains what happened to that
که چه بر سر آن پیش‌نویس
first draft. If you watched part one, you
اول آمد. اگر بخش یک را دیدید،
already know the pattern. Iranians demand
الگو را می‌شناسید. ایرانیان حکومت
constitutional government. Foreign powers
مشروطه می‌خواهند. قدرت‌های خارجی
don't like it, foreign
خوششان نمی‌آید، قدرت‌های
powers team up with local
خارجی با مستبدین
authoritarians, and the constitutional
داخلی همدست می‌شوند، و حکومت
government gets crushed. In 1906,
مشروطه سرکوب می‌شود. در ۱۹۰۶،
Iranians built a parliament.
ایرانیان مجلس ساختند.
Russia bombards it. In 1953, Iranians
روسیه آن را بمباران کرد. در ۱۹۵۳، ایرانیان
select Mosaddegh. The CIA overthrew him.
مصدق را انتخاب کردند. سیا او را سرنگون کرد.
The same cycle, but 1979 was different.
همان چرخه، اما ۱۹۷۹ فرق داشت.
In 1979, Iranians won. The
در ۱۹۷۹، ایرانیان پیروز شدند.
Shah fled. The revolution
شاه فرار کرد. انقلاب
succeeded. No foreign army stopped them.
پیروز شد. هیچ ارتش خارجی جلویشان را نگرفت.
And then, Iranians built a
و بعد، ایرانیان سیستمی
system even harder to challenge
ساختند که به چالش کشیدنش
than the one they just overthrew. The
سخت‌تر از آن بود که سرنگون کردند. سوال
real question isn't what America did to
واقعی این نیست که آمریکا با ایران چه کرد،
Iran, it's what Iran did
این است که ایران با خودش
to itself. February 1979, millions
چه کرد. فوریه ۱۹۷۹، میلیون‌ها نفر
marched in the streets. The
در خیابان‌ها راهپیمایی کردند.
Shah is gone. The coalition that
شاه رفته. ائتلافی که
toppled him included everyone. Liberals,
او را سرنگون کرد همه را شامل می‌شد. لیبرال‌ها،
nationalists, communists,
ملی‌گراها، کمونیست‌ها،
Islamists, all united against the
اسلام‌گراها، همه متحد علیه
monarchy. The early documents promised
سلطنت. اسناد اولیه وعده دادند
what they all fought for.
آنچه همه برایش جنگیدند.
Democracy. The first draft was
دموکراسی. پیش‌نویس اول را
written by moderates, lawyers, academics,
میانه‌روها نوشتند، وکلا، دانشگاهیان،
and secular nationalists.
و ملی‌گراهای سکولار.
People who wanted a republic
کسانی که یک جمهوری می‌خواستند
without clerical rule. It looked like a
بدون حکومت روحانیون. شبیه یک
normal parliamentary
دموکراسی پارلمانی
democracy. A strong Majlis,
معمولی بود. مجلس قوی،
elected president with real power,
رئیس‌جمهور منتخب با قدرت واقعی،
independent courts. Clerics
دادگاه‌های مستقل. روحانیون
get religious authority, but
اختیار مذهبی داشتند، اما
not political supremacy. No supreme
نه برتری سیاسی. اصلاً مفهوم
leader concept at all.
رهبری وجود نداشت.
Khomeini rejected it. He said,
خمینی آن را رد کرد. گفت،
"We need an elected assembly of experts
«ما به یک مجلس خبرگان منتخب نیاز داریم
to write a proper Islamic constitution."
تا یک قانون اساسی اسلامی درست بنویسد.»
An elected assembly sounds democratic.
مجلس منتخب دموکراتیک به نظر می‌رسد.
Khomeini's people controlled
افراد خمینی قوانین
the election rules. The rules
انتخابات را کنترل کردند. قوانین
were written to heavily favour clerics.
به نفع روحانیون نوشته شده بود.
As a result, Khomeini's
در نتیجه، طرفداران خمینی
supporters took 55 out of 73 seats.
۵۵ کرسی از ۷۳ کرسی را گرفتند.
The secular group saw what was happening.
گروه‌های سکولار دیدند چه اتفاقی می‌افتد.
They boycotted. They
تحریم کردند.
called it rigged. The assembly
گفتند تقلب است. مجلس
then wrote "Velayat-e Faqih" into the
بعد «ولایت فقیه» را در
constitution. They
قانون اساسی نوشت.
created a supreme leader with
یک رهبر با قدرت
ultimate power over everything. Then came
نهایی بر همه چیز ایجاد کردند. بعد
a referendum in December
یک همه‌پرسی در دسامبر
1979. The timing matters
۱۹۷۹ آمد. زمان‌بندی
here. This was the middle of the hostage
مهم است. این وسط بحران گروگان‌گیری
crisis. Students had
بود. دانشجویان
seized the American embassy.
سفارت آمریکا را گرفته بودند.
Revolutionary fever was at its highest.
تب انقلابی در اوج بود.
The question on the
سوال روی برگه رأی
ballot wasn't "Do you approve
این نبود که «آیا این قانون
this specific constitution?" It was "Are
اساسی خاص را تأیید می‌کنید؟» این بود که «آیا
you for the Islamic
طرفدار جمهوری
Republic or against it?"
اسلامی هستید یا مخالف؟»
Voting no meant voting against the
رأی نه یعنی رأی علیه
revolution. The form looked
انقلاب. شکل دموکراتیک
democratic, but the substance
به نظر می‌رسید، اما محتوا
was a hijacking. Now I need to show you
یک ربودن بود. حالا باید مکانیسم را نشانتان بدهم،
the mechanism, because
چون وقتی ببینید،
once you see it, you'll
می‌فهمید چرا هر
understand why every Iranian election
انتخاباتی در ایران از ۱۹۷۹
since 1979 has been theatre.
تئاتر بوده است.
This is the Guardian Council.
این شورای نگهبان است.
12 people with two main powers. Power 1.
۱۲ نفر با دو قدرت اصلی. قدرت ۱.
They can veto any law
می‌توانند هر قانونی را که
parliament passes if they say it
مجلس تصویب می‌کند وتو کنند اگر بگویند
violates Islam or the constitution. Power
اسلام یا قانون اساسی را نقض می‌کند. قدرت
2. They can disqualify any
۲. می‌توانند هر کاندیدایی را
candidate before voters even
قبل از اینکه رأی‌دهندگان
see their name on the ballot. If the
اسمشان را روی برگه ببینند رد صلاحیت کنند. اگر
Guardian Council says "No",
شورای نگهبان بگوید «نه»،
you don't run. Six members
کاندید نمی‌شوید. شش عضو
are clerics appointed directly by the
روحانی هستند که مستقیماً توسط
supreme leader. The other six are
رهبر منصوب می‌شوند. شش تای دیگر
jurists, nominated by
حقوقدان هستند، نامزد شده توسط
the head of the judiciary, who is also
رئیس قوه قضائیه، که او هم
appointed by the supreme
توسط رهبر
leader. Then parliament confirms
منصوب می‌شود. بعد مجلس آنها را
them. But those parliament members were
تأیید می‌کند. اما آن نمایندگان مجلس
already vetted by the
قبلاً توسط شورای
Guardian Council in the previous
نگهبان در انتخابات قبلی
election. Everyone in power was chosen by
بررسی شده بودند. هر کسی که قدرت دارد توسط کسی
someone who was chosen by
انتخاب شده که توسط
the supreme leader. The Shah
رهبر انتخاب شده. شاه
needed tanks to shut down parliament. The
به تانک نیاز داشت تا مجلس را ببندد.
Islamic Republic doesn't
جمهوری اسلامی
need tanks. They just need to
به تانک نیاز ندارد. فقط باید
make sure the right people get elected in
مطمئن شوند افراد درست از اول
the first place. In
انتخاب شوند. در
2016, the Guardian Council
۲۰۱۶، شورای نگهبان
disqualified 99% of reformist candidates
۹۹ درصد کاندیداهای اصلاح‌طلب را
for parliament. 3000
برای مجلس رد صلاحیت کرد. ۳۰۰۰
reformists registered. Only
اصلاح‌طلب ثبت‌نام کردند. فقط
30 were approved. They've disqualified
۳۰ نفر تأیید شدند. رفسنجانی
former president Rafsanjani, one of the founders of
رئیس‌جمهور سابق، یکی از بنیان‌گذاران
the Islamic Republic. They've
جمهوری اسلامی را رد صلاحیت کردند.
disqualified Hassan Khomeini, Ayatollah
حسن خمینی، نوه خود آیت‌الله
Khomeini's own grandson.
خمینی را رد صلاحیت کردند.
That's the political half of the machine.
این نیمه سیاسی ماشین است.
The other half is economic. The
نیمه دیگر اقتصادی است.
revolutionary guards,
سپاه پاسداران،
the IRGC, started as a military force.
به عنوان یک نیروی نظامی شروع کرد.
Now they're also a giant
حالا یک امپراتوری تجاری
business empire. Together with the
غول‌پیکر هم هست. همراه با
Bonyads, huge religious foundations that
بنیادها، نهادهای مذهبی بزرگ که
act like conglomerates, they control
مثل هلدینگ عمل می‌کنند، بین
between 20 and 40% of
۲۰ تا ۴۰ درصد
Iran's entire economy. Today millions of
کل اقتصاد ایران را کنترل می‌کنند. امروز میلیون‌ها
Iranians work for these
ایرانی برای این
companies. Their families depend on
شرکت‌ها کار می‌کنند. خانواده‌هایشان به
paychecks from the very system they're
حقوقی وابسته‌اند که از همان سیستمی می‌آید
protesting against. If you oppose the
که علیهش اعتراض می‌کنند. اگر با رژیم
regime, you might also
مخالفت کنید، شاید
be opposing your own employer. The system
با کارفرمای خودتان هم مخالفت کنید. سیستم
doesn't just control who can
فقط کنترل نمی‌کند چه کسی می‌تواند
run for office, it controls
کاندید شود، کنترل می‌کند
who can eat. So the oppressive theocracy
چه کسی می‌تواند نان بخورد. پس روایت تئوکراسی
story is right about the
سرکوبگر درباره
mechanisms. The Guardian Council
مکانیسم‌ها درست است. شورای نگهبان
is real, the economic control is real,
واقعی است، کنترل اقتصادی واقعی است،
and the suppression is real
و سرکوب هم واقعی
as well. But it goes wrong
است. اما اشتباه می‌شود
when people say that this is some
وقتی مردم می‌گویند این یک
inevitable cultural destiny, as if
سرنوشت فرهنگی اجتناب‌ناپذیر است، انگار
Iranians are naturally
ایرانیان ذاتاً
suited to theocracy, as if they never
برای تئوکراسی ساخته شده‌اند، انگار هرگز
wanted anything else. Look
چیز دیگری نخواسته‌اند.
at the history. Iran had a
به تاریخ نگاه کنید. ایران
constitutional democracy in 1906 demanded
دموکراسی مشروطه در ۱۹۰۶ داشت که
by Iranians themselves,
خود ایرانیان خواستند،
not given by colonizers.
نه هدیه استعمارگران.
Egypt's parliament was set up under
مجلس مصر زیر نظارت
British supervision. Iraq's 1925
بریتانیا تشکیل شد. قانون اساسی ۱۹۲۵
constitution was drafted
عراق توسط
by British mandatory parties. Iran's 1906
مقامات قیمومیت بریتانیا نوشته شد. قانون اساسی ۱۹۰۶
constitution was
ایران توسط
written by revolutionaries,
انقلابیون نوشته شد،
who took sanctuary in the British embassy
که در سفارت بریتانیا پناه گرفتند
to demand it. The
تا آن را بخواهند.
protests happening right now,
اعتراضاتی که الان می‌شود،
they're not a weird outlier. They're the
یک استثنای عجیب نیست. ادامه
continuation of a 120
یک مبارزه ۱۲۰
year old fight. They
ساله است.
talk about democracy, pluralism, human
از دموکراسی، پلورالیسم، حقوق
rights, civil society.
بشر، جامعه مدنی حرف می‌زنند.
That language didn't come from
این زبان از
foreign NGOs. It came from 120 years of
NGOهای خارجی نیامده. از ۱۲۰ سال
Iranians demanding the same
ایرانیانی آمده که همان
thing their great grandparents
چیزی را می‌خواستند که پدربزرگ‌هایشان
demanded in 1906. That's not cultural
در ۱۹۰۶ خواستند. این شکست فرهنگی
failure. That's Iranian
نیست. این فرهنگ سیاسی
political culture surviving
ایرانی است که زنده مانده
despite 120 years of suppression. 14,000
با وجود ۱۲۰ سال سرکوب. ۱۴,۰۰۰
people camped in the
نفر در باغ
British embassy garden demanding
سفارت بریتانیا چادر زدند و
a parliament in 1906. In 1951, a
مجلس خواستند در ۱۹۰۶. در ۱۹۵۱،
unanimous majlis voted to
مجلس به اتفاق آرا رأی داد به
nationalize oil. June 2009,
ملی کردن نفت. ژوئن ۲۰۰۹،
presidential elections. Official results
انتخابات ریاست جمهوری. نتایج رسمی
say Ahmadinejad won in a
گفت احمدی‌نژاد با اختلاف
landslide. Millions believed
زیاد برنده شد. میلیون‌ها نفر
it was stolen and three million people
باور کردند تقلب شده و سه میلیون نفر
took to the streets in Tehran
در تهران به خیابان آمدند
chanting, "Where is my vote?"
و فریاد زدند «رأی من کو؟»
The government's response showed the
واکنش دولت ماشین را
machine. When the regime
نشان داد. وقتی رژیم
wants to crush protests without
می‌خواهد اعتراضات را بدون
using the army, they send the Basij.
ارتش سرکوب کند، بسیج را می‌فرستد.
Volunteer militias
شبه‌نظامیان داوطلب
loyal to the supreme leader,
وفادار به رهبر،
ideologically committed civilians
غیرنظامیان ایدئولوژیک
organized in every neighborhood,
سازمان‌دهی شده در هر محله،
workplace and university.
محل کار و دانشگاه.
Between 70 and 110 civilians were killed.
بین ۷۰ تا ۱۱۰ غیرنظامی کشته شدند.
The leaders of the Green
رهبران جنبش
Movement, the opposition
سبز، کاندیداهای اپوزیسیون
candidates who said the election was
که گفتند انتخابات تقلب
stolen, were put under house arrest.
شده، تحت حصر خانگی قرار گرفتند.
They're still there today,
هنوز هم آنجا هستند،
16 years later. November 2019, the
۱۶ سال بعد. نوامبر ۲۰۱۹،
government suddenly
دولت ناگهان
raises fuel prices overnight.
قیمت بنزین را یک شبه بالا برد.
Protests explode in 21 cities within
اعتراضات در ۲۱ شهر ظرف
hours. The response was
چند ساعت منفجر شد. واکنش
the most violent since 1979.
خشن‌ترین از ۱۹۷۹ بود.
First, total internet blackout. Then,
اول، قطع کامل اینترنت. بعد،
shoot to kill orders. Amnesty
دستور تیر. عفو
International named around
بین‌الملل حدود
300 dead. Some sources inside the
۳۰۰ کشته اعلام کرد. برخی منابع داخل
government said the death toll was closer
دولت گفتند تعداد کشته‌ها نزدیک
to 1500. The supreme
۱۵۰۰ بود. رهبر
leader reportedly told advisers, "The
ظاهراً به مشاوران گفت، «جمهوری
Islamic republic is in
اسلامی در خطر
danger. Stop the protests by any
است. اعتراضات را به هر
means necessary." September 2022, Mahsa
قیمتی متوقف کنید.» سپتامبر ۲۰۲۲، مهسا
Amini dies in morality
امینی در بازداشت گشت
police custody. Her crime was
ارشاد جان باخت. جرمش
wearing her hijab improperly. Protests
پوشیدن حجاب نامناسب بود. اعتراضات
erupt in 150 cities, people chanting
در ۱۵۰ شهر شعله‌ور شد، مردم فریاد
"women, life, freedom."
می‌زدند «زن، زندگی، آزادی.»
Over 500 people were killed, 22,000
بیش از ۵۰۰ نفر کشته شدند، ۲۲,۰۰۰
detained, at least seven publicly
بازداشت شدند، حداقل هفت نفر علناً
executed. The UN called it
اعدام شدند. سازمان ملل آن را
crimes against humanity. The women
جنایت علیه بشریت خواند. زنانی که
leading the protests weren't only
رهبری اعتراضات را داشتند فقط
fighting about the hijab,
برای حجاب نمی‌جنگیدند،
they were using the same constitutional
همان زبان مشروطه‌خواهی را
language their
استفاده می‌کردند که
grandparents used. The same demand for
پدربزرگ‌هایشان استفاده کردند. همان خواسته برای
limits on arbitrary power. The same fight
محدود کردن قدرت خودسرانه. همان مبارزه‌ای
that started in 1906.
که در ۱۹۰۶ شروع شد.
And in December 2025,
و در دسامبر ۲۰۲۵،
the rial collapses. Food prices went up
ریال سقوط کرد. قیمت غذا ۷۲
by 72 percent, inflation
درصد بالا رفت، تورم
around 40 percent. But this
حدود ۴۰ درصد. اما این
time something fundamental changed. The
بار چیز اساسی عوض شد.
Bazaaris, the traditional
بازاریان، طبقه تاجر
merchant class, the people the
سنتی، کسانی که جمهوری
Islamic republic was partially built to
اسلامی تا حدی برای حفاظتشان
protect, started closing
ساخته شده بود، شروع به بستن
their shops. They joined the
مغازه‌هایشان کردند. به
protests. When the Bazaaris turn against
اعتراضات پیوستند. وقتی بازاریان علیه
you, the regime has lost
شما بر می‌گردند، رژیم چیزی را
something it can't replace.
از دست داده که جایگزین ندارد.
These aren't students or activists. These
اینها دانشجو یا فعال نیستند. اینها
were supposed to be the regime's base.
قرار بود پایگاه رژیم باشند.
Iran human rights documented over 3,400
سازمان حقوق بشر ایران بیش از ۳,۴۰۰
killed in the first two
کشته در دو هفته
weeks. Another internet blackout,
اول ثبت کرد. یک قطع اینترنت دیگر،
darkness, then violence. Every protest
تاریکی، بعد خشونت. هر اعتراضی
demands the same things.
همان چیزها را می‌خواهد.
Fair elections, press freedom,
انتخابات عادلانه، آزادی مطبوعات،
economic accountability, women's rights.
پاسخگویی اقتصادی، حقوق زنان.
Every response uses the same toolkit.
هر واکنشی همان ابزارها را استفاده می‌کند.
Russian Cossacks bombarded parliament in
قزاق‌های روس مجلس را در
1908. CIA funded mobs in
۱۹۰۸ بمباران کردند. اوباش با پول سیا در
1953. Basij with iron rods in
۱۹۵۳. بسیج با میله‌های آهنی در
2009. Snipers and internet blackouts in
۲۰۰۹. تک‌تیراندازها و قطع اینترنت در
2019. That's the cycle Iran
۲۰۱۹. این چرخه‌ای است که ایران
has been trapped in for 120
۱۲۰ سال در آن گیر
years. And the 1979 constitution was
کرده. و قانون اساسی ۱۹۷۹ طراحی شد
designed to make sure it
تا مطمئن شود هرگز
never breaks. So what do the
نشکند. پس منابع
sources actually show? It's not all
واقعاً چه نشان می‌دهند؟ همه‌اش تقصیر
America's fault that turns
آمریکا نیست که ایرانیان را
Iranians into passive victims.
قربانیان منفعل می‌کند.
It ignores the internal collaborators,
همکاران داخلی را نادیده می‌گیرد،
the elite power
کشمکش‌های
struggles, the control mechanisms
قدرت نخبگان، مکانیسم‌های کنترلی که
Iranians built to control other Iranians.
ایرانیان برای کنترل ایرانیان دیگر ساختند.
1979 wasn't a foreign
۱۹۷۹ کودتای خارجی
coup. Iranians did this to
نبود. ایرانیان این را با خودشان
themselves. It's not Iran is hopelessly
کردند. ایران ناامیدانه تئوکراتیک
theocratic, that erases
نیست، این ۱۲۰ سال
120 years of people fighting for
مبارزه مردم برای
constitutional limits. It pretends
محدودیت‌های مشروطه را پاک می‌کند. تظاهر
authoritarianism is some deep cultural
می‌کند استبداد یک سرنوشت
destiny. The real pattern is
فرهنگی عمیق است. الگوی واقعی
this. Iranians demand constitutional
این است. ایرانیان حکومت مشروطه
government that threatens
می‌خواهند که هر کسی که قدرت دارد را
whoever holds power. Internal
تهدید می‌کند. نخبگان داخلی
elites team up with whoever helps them
با هر کسی که کمک می‌کند در قدرت بمانند
stay in power. Sometimes
همدست می‌شوند. گاهی
foreign, sometimes not.
خارجی، گاهی نه.
Violent suppression follows and that
سرکوب خشن می‌آید و آن
trauma radicalizes the
تروما نسل بعدی را
next generation. The common
رادیکال می‌کند. تهدید
threat isn't foreign meddling or Islamic
مشترک مداخله خارجی یا فرهنگ
culture. It's the refusal
اسلامی نیست. امتناع
of people in power to accept
صاحبان قدرت از پذیرش
any real limits on that power. Both big
هر محدودیت واقعی بر آن قدرت است. هر دو
narratives are
روایت بزرگ
comforting. That's why they survive.
آرامش‌بخش‌اند. به همین دلیل زنده می‌مانند.
The truth is messier. External
حقیقت درهم‌تر است. مداخله
intervention and internal mechanisms
خارجی و مکانیسم‌های داخلی
created a self reinforcing
یک چرخه خود-تقویت‌کننده
cycle that Iranians keep trying and dying
ساختند که ایرانیان مدام تلاش و مُردن
to break. Right now
برای شکستنش را ادامه می‌دهند. همین الان
Iranians are in the streets.
ایرانیان در خیابان‌اند.
Again, dying again. The regime blames
دوباره، دوباره می‌میرند. رژیم توطئه‌های
foreign conspiracies. Again,
خارجی را مقصر می‌داند. دوباره،
the West shakes its head at
غرب سرش را برای
the theocracy. Again, and the real story,
تئوکراسی تکان می‌دهد. دوباره، و داستان واقعی،
120 years of constitutional
۱۲۰ سال خواسته‌های مشروطه
demands met with violence,
که با خشونت جواب گرفته،
gets buried again. If you understand what
دوباره دفن می‌شود. اگر بفهمید چه
happened to that first
بر سر آن پیش‌نویس
draft in 1979, you understand
اول در ۱۹۷۹ آمد،
something much bigger than Iran. You
چیزی خیلی بزرگ‌تر از ایران را می‌فهمید.
understand how revolutions
می‌فهمید چطور انقلاب‌ها
get hijacked, how democratic
ربوده می‌شوند، چطور جنبش‌های
movements get captured by people they
دموکراتیک توسط کسانی که علیهشان
were fighting against, how the promise of
می‌جنگیدند تصاحب می‌شوند، چطور وعده
freedom can be used to
آزادی می‌تواند برای
build a prison. That pattern is happening
ساختن یک زندان استفاده شود. این الگو الان
right now in countries
در کشورهایی دارد می‌شود
you've never heard of. Iran's
که اسمشان را نشنیده‌اید. نسخه
version is just the most documented. The
ایران فقط مستندترین است.
Bazaars closing their
بازاریانی که
shops in 2025 are the great
در ۲۰۲۵ مغازه‌هایشان را می‌بندند نوه‌های
grandchildren of the merchants who took
همان تاجرانی هستند که در
sanctuary in the British
سفارت بریتانیا
Embassy in 1906. If this helped you
در ۱۹۰۶ پناه گرفتند. اگر این کمک کرد
understand something about Iran or about
چیزی درباره ایران یا درباره
how power actually works, hit
نحوه کار قدرت بفهمید،
subscribe. I'm going to keep
سابسکرایب کنید. من به کندوکاو
digging into primary sources instead of
در منابع اولیه ادامه می‌دهم به جای
just repeating what
تکرار حرف‌های
everyone else says. And drop a
بقیه. و کامنت بگذارید.
comment. What historical document do you
کدام سند تاریخی را می‌خواهید
want me to dig in next?
بررسی کنم؟